

CONTACT

+49 15214388810

orousramdane@gmail.com

in LinkedIn

GitHub

Poststrasse 28, 01159, Dresden, Germany

EXPERTISE

Functional:

- Econometrics
- **Development Research**
- Impact Evaluation
- Machine learning & statistical modelling
- Data Collection, Analytics, Visualisation
- Environmental policy & regulation
- Sustainability strategy development
- Sustainability assessment
- E&S risks & impact assessment

Industry:

- Government / Public sector
- Climate-smart agriculture
- Agri-food & land use
- Sustainable production & consumption
- **ESG Reporting**
- Circular economy

COMPETENCIES

- Communication & presentation
- Project management
- Stakeholder engagement
- Problem solving
- Teamwork

LANGUAGES

French native fluent [C2] English professional [B1] German basic [A1] Arabic

RAMOUDANE **OROU SANNOU**

Environmental Economist & Data Scientist

I am an Environmental Economist with a skillset encompassing analytical and quantitative abilities. My 5+ years of research and consulting experience spans diverse fields, including development economics, sustainability science, and socio-economic and environmental impact assessments and methods. I have contributed to and managed development research projects in several international organisations with a deep-rooted passion for leveraging data science to generate valuable evidence to enable informed decision-making.

EDUCATION

- Technical University of Dresden | PhD in Integrated Management of Environmental Resources Germany | 05/2021 - 06/2024 | Chair of Environmental Management and Accounting
- Frankfurt School of Finance & Management | Certified Expert in Sustainable Finance Germany | 03/2023 - 09/2023
- Technical University of Dresden | Postgraduate Diploma of Environmental Management Germany | 01/2018 - 07/2018 | Best Paper Award
- University of Parakou | M.Sc. & B.Sc. in Rural Economics & Sociology Benin | 10/2011 - 07/2017 | Honors

WORK EXPERIENCE – EMPLOYMENT

United Nations University | Researcher at the Institute for Integrated management of material Fluxes and of Resources (UNU-FLORES)

Dresden | 05/2021 - present

My research delves into the intricate interplay between temporal, spatial, economic, and environmental dimensions of sustainability, providing valuable insights for measuring social sustainability to achieve the SGDs.

Key achievements:

- Successfully completed the manuscript of an upcoming scientific paper in a scientific journal, utilizing panel data regression to analyze the impact of a large-scale land restoration innovation on
- Authored a scientific paper published in a leading peer-reviewed journal, employing qualitative content analysis and machine learning techniques to extract pertinent social sustainability indicators from extensive scientific literature.
- Collected and analysed primary data for an upcoming paper on the impact of organizational innovations on women Shea producers in Ghana.
- Advancing the Institute's implementation plan through effective management of my research project focusing on the development of resilient agri-food systems and the enhancement of sustainability assessment methods.
- United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA) | Data Fellow International Specialist Ouagadougou | 09/2019 - 04/2021

Managed UNFPA's research & development activities on Civil Registration and Vital Statistics (CRVS) in Burkina Faso. Through comprehensive analyses, I successfully unravelled the proximate determinants of vital events' registration and produced several invaluable knowledge products concerning vital statistics in Burkina Faso. My contributions significantly strengthened the understanding of CRVS systems and their impact on public health and policymaking, ultimately paving the way for evidencebased solutions and improvements in vital event registration processes.

Key achievements:

- Automation of Birth Registration Analysis: Developed an efficient R code to automate the generation of tables and graphs showcasing the completeness of birth registration, facilitating accurate reporting and the understanding of birth registration patterns.
- Statistical Modeling for Birth Registration: Utilized advanced statistical modelling techniques to predict the effects of maternal age and usual residence on birth registration and certificate detention in West and Central African countries.
- Training in R for National Statisticians: Delivered comprehensive hands-on training sessions on R programming to 10+ statisticians from the National Statistics Offices of Morocco and Burkina Faso
- Roll-out of digital birth registration technology with private sector partner iCivil: Supported the successful deployment of iCivil, a cutting-edge technology for systematic birth, marriage, and death registration. By overseeing the implementation of mobile applications, computer software, and a data server, I facilitated streamlined data generation and improved registration processes, contributing to the registration of over 3000 births in 6 months from 3 pilot villages.

IT SKILLS

Data analysis:

R advanced
Python advanced
SQL good
Excel advanced
Stata Beginner

Visualization:

ggplot2 advanced
Matplotlib good
Tableau good
PowerPoint advanced

Other:

- ArcGIS
- Google Earth Engine
- · Microsoft Planetary Computer

PUBLICATIONS

- Orou Sannou, R., Kirschke, S., Günther, E., 2023. Integrating the social perspective into the sustainability assessment of agrifood systems: A review of indicators. Sustainable Production and Consumption. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.spc.2023.05.014
- Orou Sannou R., et al. (forthcoming), Large-scale Innovation in Agri-food Systems for Food Security: Evidence from the Great Green Wall Initiative Countries.

CERTIFICATES (SELECTION)

- Manage Impact Evaluations (World Bank)
- Strategic Planning/Results-based Management (University of Wolverhampton)
- Project Management (TU Dresden)
- Data Scientist with R (DataCamp)
- Statistician with R (DataCamp)
- Data Science with Python (IBM)
- Social & Economic Networks Analysis and Modeling (Stanford University - Coursera)

HOBBIES

- Reading novels
- Cooking
- Hiking
- Fitness

Dresden, 07/10/2023 Ramoudane Orou Sannou

WORK EXPERIENCE - EMPLOYMENT (CONTD)

 African Union Commission | Researcher at the Human Resources, Science & Technology Department Addis-Ababa | 08/2018 – 08/2019

Contributed to several projects involving research and data analysis to enable senior management to develop policies and programs on youth development at the continental level.

Key achievements:

- State of African Youth Report 2019 (SoAYR): Led a team of 14 Researchers in drafting the State of
 African Youth Report 2019, demonstrating exceptional skills in data collection, centralization,
 analysis, and visualization. Successfully gathered and analyzed data from 55 African countries,
 presenting insightful indicators that provided a comprehensive understanding of youth-related
 issues across the continent.
- Shaping the "1 million Youth by 2021" Initiative: Played a crucial role in shaping the African Union Commission's (AUC) "1 million Youth by 2021" initiative. Conducted a rigorous feasibility study and performed data analysis and visualization on multiple development indicators, providing essential evidence to support strategic actions aimed at empowering and uplifting 1 million youth across Africa.
- Development Data Management: Initiated and efficiently managed the AUC's developmentrelated data and data visualization central hub on the <u>Humanitarian Data Exchange (HDX) web</u> <u>platform</u>. This ensured seamless data access and visualization, facilitating evidence-based decision-making and fostering collaboration among various stakeholders.

WORK EXPERIENCE - FREELANCE

The Commonwealth Secretariat | Data Science Consultant Home-based | Multiple assignments since 2022

Delivered workshop sessions on data science and its applications in development research at Commonwealth Data Science and Innovation Workshops across the Caribbean and Africa.

International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD) | Research Analyst at the Independent Office
of Evaluation

Home-based | 04/2021 - 09/2021

Played a key role in the <u>sub-regional evaluation of IFAD operations</u> in 6 fragile countries in West Africa (G5 Sahel Countries plus Northern Nigeria). Conducted comprehensive desk reviews of 100+ project reports, performed data analysis, fragility risks analysis, and generated insightful reports.

Numbers and People Synergy (NAPS) | Data Science Consultant

Home-based | Multiple assignments since 2019

Executed data cleaning and batch calculations to impute missing values, ensuring cross-country comparability of indicators in various Youth Development Indices (e.g., Pakistan, Australia, ASEAN, African Union, Sports & SDGs, etc.).

VOLUNTEERING

• World Food Forum (WFF) | Young Scientist

Home-based | 05/2023 - present

Providing the World Food Forum (WFF) with scientific evidence and technical expertise for effective implementation of initiatives targeting agrifood systems transformation in alignment with the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).

Global Reporting Initiative (GRI) | Subject Matter Expert

Home-based | 01/2023 - 02/2023

Conducted peer review of the French translation of the GRI 13 Sector Standard on Agriculture, Aquaculture, and Fishing.

 International Association of students in Agricultural and related Sciences (IAAS) | Africa Regional Director

Multiple countries | 12/2016 - 01/2018

Successfully devised and executed a strategic plan, establishing new IAAS chapters across Senegal, Burkina Faso, Cameroon, Burundi, Tanzania, and South Africa.